<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <meta>
    <source>Gray 1950</source>
    <processed_by>
      <processor process_type="format_conversion">Cui, Hong using Text2XML java application init commit r86, validated against beeSchema.xsd revision f0a80a8516a06e51224d01314403eb26d60f881d</processor>
    </processed_by>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>rubus</genus_name>
    <species_name>vermontanus</species_name>
    <species_authority>blanch.</species_authority>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;tribe rubeae;genus rubus;subgenus eubatus;section setosi;species vermontanus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <other_name>(of vermont)</other_name>
  <number>127</number>
  <description>Habitally like nos. 120 and 123 but with sparser armature; primocanes erect to depressed, 0.2-1.5 m. high, with very few to 150 firm slender acerose prickles per dm., these without interspersed glands and usually without finer bristles; floricane-leaves 5-foliolate, their petioles more or less prickly; leaflets ovate-lanceolate, ovate or ovate-oblong, tapering to acuminate apex, two-fifths to three-fifths as broad as long, sharply double-serrate, thinnish, dull or barely sublustrous, glabrous above, pale to deeper green and glabrous beneath; inflorescence varying from a simple raceme to a forking corymb; the pedicels unarmed or rarely with few short setae, mostly glandless (occasionally with few glands); lower bracts foliaceous, upper reduced and stipule-like; petals 1-1.5 cm. long, 4-8 mm. broad; fruit about 1 cm. in diameter, juicy but sour. (Incl. R. junceus Blanch., plants "with a flimsy look"; R. viridifrons Bailey, i.e., R. vermontanus, var. viridifolius Blanch., with dark and sublustrous leaves and with some glands on pedicels, a "guise" which "has no separate range or habitat.......In a single collecting ....... one may distinguish both kinds."</description>
  <habitat_elevation_distribution_or_ecology>Dry to moist thickets, clearings, etc., plastic but forming a consistent series of interlocked minor trends, Nfld. to Ont., s. to N.S., s. N.E., N.Y., n. Pa., Mich., Wisc. and Minn. Fl. mid-June-mid.-Aug.; fr. late July-Sept.</habitat_elevation_distribution_or_ecology>
  <discussion>Bailey; R. navus, R. unanimous and R. superioris Bailey; R. spectatus Bailey, with setose pedicels; R. apparatus Bailey, with as few prickles as R. junceus; R. malus Bailey, with foliage and glandular pedicels as in R. viridifrons but collected in N.B. instead of Vt.; R. offectus Bailey, suggesting R. junceus with some setae on a few pedicels; R. suppar Bailey, like R. viridifrons but with dull leaves; R. quebecensis Bailey, nearly unarmed; R. Deaneanus Bailey; R. singulus Bailey, with leaflets slightly narrower than in R. suppar)</discussion>
</treatment>

