<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <meta>
    <source>Gray 1950</source>
    <processed_by>
      <processor process_type="format_conversion">Cui, Hong using Text2XML java application init commit r86, validated against beeSchema.xsd revision f0a80a8516a06e51224d01314403eb26d60f881d</processor>
    </processed_by>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <section_name>canadenses</section_name>
    <section_authority>bailey</section_authority>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;tribe rubeae;genus rubus;subgenus eubatus;section canadenses;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <other_name>(see p. 824)</other_name>
  <description>a. Canes prickleless (very rarely with remote small prickles); petiole of primocane-leaf unarmed or nearly so; flowers racemose (up to 25), on naked pedicels; wide-ranging...................... 148. R. canadensis.</description>
  <description>a. Canes definitely prickly; petioles of primocane well armed; northern....... b.</description>
  <description>b. Principal inflorescence (excluding lower secondary ones) mostly 6-15-flowered, racemose or racemose-corymbose....... c.</description>
  <description>c. Bracteal leaflets or leaves toothed essentially to base.</description>
  <description>Prickles of primocanes 2-10 per dm.; midrib of terminal primocane-leaflet unarmed; median leaflets cuneate or subcuneate at base, their petiolules 3-13 mm. long; pedicels of cylindric raceme 1-3.5 cm. long, unarmed............................... 149. R. amicalis.</description>
  <description>Prickles of primocanes 30-100 per dm.; midrib of terminal primocane-leaflet usually somewhat prickly beneath; median leaflets broadly rounded at base, their petiolules 0.6-3 cm. long; pedicels of broad-topped racemose corymb mostly 2-7 cm. long, frequently armed.... 150. R. elegantulus.</description>
  <description>c. Bracteal leaves or leaflets nearly or quite entire toward the cuneate base; prickles of primocane 50-200 per dm............................ 151. R. miscix.</description>
  <description>b. Principal inflorescences strongly corymbiform, 2-few-flowered.</description>
  <description>Coarser prickles of primocane acicular or slenderly subulate; corymb barely or not at all exceeding the leaves, the stiff pedicels mostly 0.5-3 cm. long; wide-ranging northw......................... 152. R. Kennedyanus</description>
  <description>Coarser prickles of primocane broad-based; corymb greatly overtopping leaves, its filiform pedicels mostly 3.5-6 cm. long; local in Me.......... 153. R.  multilicius.</description>
</treatment>

