<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <meta>
    <source>Gray 1950</source>
    <processed_by>
      <processor process_type="format_conversion">Cui, Hong using Text2XML java application init commit r86, validated against beeSchema.xsd revision f0a80a8516a06e51224d01314403eb26d60f881d</processor>
    </processed_by>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>rubus</genus_name>
    <species_name>glandicaulis</species_name>
    <species_authority>blanch,</species_authority>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;tribe rubeae;genus rubus;subgenus eubatus;section alleghenienses;species glandicaulis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <other_name>(with glandular stem)</other_name>
  <number>164</number>
  <description>High arching (or through weight of snow low-arching to depressed), up to 2 m. high; primocanes coarse, angled, with acicular or slenderly subulate prickles mixed with stipitate glands; primocane-leaves with glabrous to sparsely pilose and glandular petioles and petiolules; leaflets acuminate, thinly pilose beneath, glabrous or glabrescent above, the principal veins beneath appressed-pilose or glabrescent, the terminal leaflet ovate or oval and cordate or broadly rounded at base; inflorescences racemose-corymbose, the lower pedicels often becoming forked elongate branches, the bracteal leaves or leaflets acute or acuminate; rachis and pedicels unarmed or with few setae; calyx-lobes lanceolate, often prolonged; petals oblanceolate to oblong-obovate, 0.8-1.5 cm. long, 5-8 mm. broad; fruit subglobose to subcylindric, 0.8-1.5 cm. long, of good quality. (Incl. R. frondisentis sensu Brain. &amp; Peitersen, not Blanch.; R. montpelierensis Blanch.; R. acadiensis Bailey)</description>
  <habitat_elevation_distribution_or_ecology>Dry to moist thickets and clearings, N.B. to sw. Que., s. to N.S., n. N.E. and ne. N.Y. Fl. June, July; fr. Sept.</habitat_elevation_distribution_or_ecology>
</treatment>

