<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <meta>
    <source>Gray 1950</source>
    <processed_by>
      <processor process_type="format_conversion">Cui, Hong using Text2XML java application init commit r86, validated against beeSchema.xsd revision f0a80a8516a06e51224d01314403eb26d60f881d</processor>
    </processed_by>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>rubus</genus_name>
    <species_name>dissitiflorus</species_name>
    <species_authority>fern.</species_authority>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;tribe rubeae;genus rubus;subgenus eubatus;section arguti;species dissitiflorus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <other_name>(remotely flowered)</other_name>
  <number>205</number>
  <description>Erect, 4-5 dm. high; slender tough terete canes simple, strongly armed with broad-based hooked prickles; primocane-leaves 3-foliolate, the petiole and petiolule unguiculate-armed; the leaflets coarsely rounded-dentate; terminal leaflet elliptic-ovate, acuminate, 5-6 cm. long; floricane unbranched except for flowering shoots; leaves similar to but smaller than primocane-foliage; flowers solitary on erect slender villous and prickly axillary pedicels 2-4 cm. long; broad pilose calyx-lobes 6-7 mm. long, appressed to the small globose fruit (scarcely 1 cm. thick)</description>
  <habitat_elevation_distribution_or_ecology>Calcareous bluffs, by James R., Isle of Wight Co., Va., little known. Fr. mid-June.</habitat_elevation_distribution_or_ecology>
  <discussion>—KERRIA DC. (for John Bellenden Ker, 1764-1842) JAPONICA (L.) DC. (Japanese), alternate-leaved shrub with green branches, 5 yellow petals and 5-8 dryish drupe-like achenes, and RHODOTYPOS Sieb. &amp; Zucc. (with character of a rose) SCANDENS (Thunb.) Makino (climbing; an unfortunate name), an upright shrub with opposite leaves and 4-merous flowers with large sepals, white petals and 4 black drupe-like dry fruits, are commonly cult. and occasionally spread to thickets, etc. (Introd. from e. Asia)</discussion>
</treatment>

